Good morning. Today's דף Daf is דף למד א. Daf Lamed Alef.
Today also is the day we commemorate יום השואה; Yom HaShoah; actually
fell out yesterday, but anyway, so
our learning should be לזכר נשמת l'zecher nishmas all of those who
perished in the Holocaust.
We pick up with למד עמוד ב, Lamed Amud Bet, the לכהן
בבית הפרס. l'kohen b'veis hapras. So we had
the issue about where you put the עירוב, eruv,
sorry, where you put the עירוב eruv
and what the עירוב eruv is made out of, and we dealt
with the issue about that it has to be two meals' worth,
you know, what's considered how much food is that, is it subjective,
is it a more universal standard, and then specifically the position of
סומכוס, Sumchus, it has to be able to be eaten by the
person himself or herself who's putting the עירוב, eruv, not just by
somebody else.
And now we turn to the question about the location, because the
משנה Mishna said, had dealt with the issue about a כהן Kohen
putting it in a place where כהן Kohen normally couldn't go, a
בית הפרס, Beis HaPras, which is a field that was plowed over,
a grave was plowed over and there are little bits of bone
throughout it, and it says you can put it for a כהן
Kohen there, and now the גמרא Gemara discusses why. ולכהן בבית הפרס,
U'l'kohen b'veis hapras, דאמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל מנפח אדם בית הפרס
והולך. d'amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel menapeach adam beis hapras v'holech.
A person can, who needs to cross, I mean a כהן, Kohen,
a בית הפרס, Beis HaPras, can sort of blow, you know, and
go. So like you blow the dirt right in front of you
and you see that there is
no, what do you call it, there's no, you know, there're no
chips of bone, and then you go.
Okay.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says, so therefore in theoretically it
would be possible to access it. רב יהודה בר אמי משמיה דרב
יהודה אמר בית הפרס שנידש טהור. Rav Yehuda bar Ami mishmei d'Rav
Yehuda amar beis hapras shenidash tahor. Once we're talking about this, there
are times where if it's actually been trampled through and people have
made a path through it, then it's טהור tahor because then you
could, then you could assume that any little chips of bone that
were on that path have already been crushed. I don't exactly know
why you can assume that, like little things can get lodged into
the dirt and not get crushed by people walking on them, but
anyway, the point is it's theoretically possible by blowing to get through
the בית הפרס Beis HaPras and therefore it is considered accessible by
the כהן. Kohen. Now we turn to the position of רבי יהודה
Reb Yehuda who says not only a בית הפרס, Beis HaPras, but
even a כהן Kohen can even put his עירוב eruv in a
cemetery, in a בית הקברות. Beis HaKevaros. רבי יהודה אומר אף בית
הקברות. Reb Yehuda omer af beis hakevaros.
תנא, Tanna, why is it? So the ברייתא Braisa explains מפני שיכול
לחוץ ולילך בשידה תיבה ומגדל, mipnei sheyachol lachutz v'leilech b'shida teiva u'migdal,
because the משנה Mishna just said because you can make a חציצה,
chatzitza, you can make a division and go, but the ברייתא Braisa
explains that you can do it in some type of a like
of a box or a tower, meaning you can basically put yourself
in like a carriage and be carried through, and therefore the fact
that there will be a floor underneath you will be a חציצה.
chatzitza. So if you happen to go over any graves, the טומאה
tumah will stop. You understand? You're like in a carriage, so like
a, you know, like a wagon as it were. So therefore any
טומאה tumah that you'll go over will be stopped by the underside
of the floor, and therefore it's theoretically possible for a כהן Kohen
to get there. It's assuming that the עירוב eruv is not on
a grave itself. The עירוב eruv is let's say between graves or
in a tree, but in order, but how do you get through
a cemetery to get to it? It's also
assuming, right, that, there's also an interesting point, it's also assuming that
the you don't have overhangs I guess, because if you had overhangs,
you were just assuming about the problem that you'll walk over a
grave. So if you're being carried in a wagon, the טומאה tumah
underneath will hit the floor of the wagon. It doesn't deal with
the problem that if you have like an overhang. So it's probably
assuming that you're, that you're not having overhangs, yeah.
Unless כהנים Kohanim sometimes wear barrels around them when they go into
a, yeah, they put a barrel around.
I don't understand how that works, what about their feet?
What about their feet? They're like. Their feet are walking but somehow
they do something, but
I don't understand how the barrel addresses this.
They make a barrier
around.
Oh, that's a different issue because you're not supposed to be within
four אמות amos of a grave, so that's maybe just to keep
them away from four אמות amos of the grave. But here there's
a concern that so that might be what that's about.
And you know
where the graves are today, they're well marked.
Right, they're well marked, right, exactly.
Barrels, yeah, some people do that. Also when they go to the
קבר kever of the רבי, Rebbe, you know, even though he didn't
die, they go to his grave and
the כהנים Kohanim wear this thing around them.
Right, interesting, interesting. Okay. All right, so there's a way to get
there.
It is possible that it also deals with the overhang as well,
I'm just thinking because if it has a roof, then it's a
separate space, so even if there's a roof. roof on top of
it, probably would deal with the overhang as well because it's not
a כלי. kli. רש"י Rashi makes the point that this wagon or
whatever this box that you're in is more than forty סאה, se'ah,
which takes it out of the category of a כלי. kli. So
you're probably so you're protected both from the underneath and if, you
know, you got a roof on top you're protected from the overhang,
so therefore you would be totally safe. You would go into like
this in through this self-contained unit. So the גמרא Gemara says, and
therefore so what's the debate? So why do the Rabbis disagree? So
the גמרא Gemara says, קסבר אהל זרוק שמיה אהל, Kasavar ohel zaruk
shemei ohel,
because it's of the opinion that a thrown אהל ohel is an
אהל, ohel, which basically means a אהל ohel that is not stationary.
I mean one thing you could imagine is, you know, I don't
know, you throw a, you know, you throw a plank through the
sky and it happens to pass over my head, right, and, you
know, and there's טומאה tumah underneath, so it could be us לחומרא
ולקולא, l'chumra u'lekula, does it carry the טומאה? tumah? You know, if
there's a מת meis over here and there's a flying plank in
the sky, shoo, right, and as it's passing over my head, does
it transfer the טומאה tumah if it's not stationary? Or in the
other case, does it stop the טומאה? tumah? Right, if does it
if you have something flying here? Now actually a good example of
that is a airplane, right, airplanes, which very often airports are made
near cemeteries and airplanes fly over the cemetery. So that's a seems
like a great example of an אהל זרוק. ohel zaruk. Does it
stop the טומאה tumah or does it go through? Also airplanes are
made out of metal and metal isn't חוצץ בפני הטומאה. chotzetz bifnei
hatumah. So a whole question about that, which is not a question
about how כהנים Kohanim can fly in airplanes that take off from
certain airports, which we're not going to get to right now, but
anyway that's the question about thrown. Lots of airports. So this is
not only this is not literally thrown, it's being carried but it's
not like in a fixed place, okay? And that's the question whether
that's considered to be an אהל, ohel, and would that be a
way of getting through the cemetery. ובפלוגתא דהני תנאי, u'vipalugta d'hani tannai,
and it connects to the debate of the following תנאים, tannaim, דתניא
דתנן בברייתא, d'tanya d'tnan b'rayta, הנכנס לארץ העמים בשידה תיבה ומגדל, hanichnas
l'eretz ha'amim b'shida teiva u'migdal, somebody goes into the non-Jewish land outside
the land of Israel where they treated it as טמא, tamei, and
therefore כהנים Kohanim actually were not allowed to leave the land of
Israel. And different opinions about how טמא tamei they treated it, but
according to one they treated it as if it was טומאת אהל,
tumas ohel, as if there was, you know, the ground was טמא
tamei and it caused it as if it was like, you know,
graves buried there. So therefore if you went if you went there
בשידה תיבה ומגדל, b'shida teiva u'migdal, if you went though in a
box or in some type of a carriage, רבי מטמא ורבי יוסי
ברבי יהודה מטהר. Rabbi metamei v'Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda mitaher. So רבי
Rabbi says it's your טמא tamei and רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rabbi
Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda says you're טהור. tahor. במאי קמיפלגי? bemai kamifligi? What's
the debate about? מר סבר אהל זרוק לאו שמיה אהל ומר סבר
אהל זרוק שמיה אהל. mar savar ohel zaruk lav shemei ohel u'mar
savar ohel zaruk shemei ohel. Okay, so this debate about whether when
it's being carried it's not in a fixed place is that an
אהל ohel to stop the טומאה tumah underneath it. Now I wanted
to go make a point, okay, so this is the debate and
the question is: Is it possible for a כהן Kohen to get
to the עירוב eruv or not? But everybody agrees that if the
כהן Kohen can't get to the עירוב, eruv, it's no good. Why
not? So if you take a look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi
says,
שמיה אהל, shemei ohel, four lines from the bottom רש"י Rashi says,
no I'm sorry it's three lines from the bottom, last word on
the line, ורבנן דמתניתין כרבי סבירא להו, v'rabanan d'matnitin k'Rabbi sevira lehu,
ובין רבי יהודה ובין לרבנן כסומכוס סבירא ליה. u'vein Rabbi Yehuda u'vein
l'rabanan k'Sumchos sevira lei.
So this problem that you have to be able to get to
your עירוב eruv and if it's in the cemetery it's a problem,
he says goes like סומכוס, Sumchos, דאמר מידי דחזי ליה למיכליה בההיא
שעתא בעינן. d'amar midi d'chazi lei l'meichlei b'hahu sha'ata ba'inan.
You need something that's able to be eaten, right? Remember סומכוס Sumchos
says a כהן Kohen can't use תרומה, trumah, you have to be
able to eat it. So רש"י Rashi says this idea that you
have to get to the food is part of סומכוס's Sumchos idea,
that
you
personally specifically
have to be able to eat it. תוספות Tosafot disagree. תוספות Tosafot
says there's a difference between eating it and getting to it. He
wants to say that everybody would agree you can't say that is
where you started שבת Shabbos if you can't get there. Okay, if
it's out of reach and you can't get there, then everybody would
agree you can't start שבת. Shabbos. The debate of סומכוס Sumchos and
the חכמים Chachamim was: Is it enough that someone can eat it
or do you have to be able to eat it? But everybody
says תוספות Tosafot would agree you have to be able to get
there. So תוספות Tosafot says this issue of stuff for כהן Kohen
in a cemetery is a problem according to everyone. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara continues, והא דתניא רבי יהודה אומר, v'ha d'tanya Rabbi
Yehuda omer, we taught in the ברייתא, brayta, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
says, not just case of a cemetery but top of ל"א ע"א,
lamed-aleph amud-aleph,
מערבין לכהן טהור
בתרומה טהורה בקבר. mearvin l'kohen tahor b'trumah tehora b'kever. That if a
כהן Kohen is טהור, tahor, you can put תרומה טהורה trumah tehora
right on a grave. Now of course the question is how can
you put תרומה טהורה trumah tehora on a grave and it remain
טהור? tahor? So the גמרא Gemara will get to it, but you
have
תרומה טהורה trumah tehora right on a grave. So on the one
hand it's more problematic because it's right on the grave and we're
talking about תרומה, trumah, and if תרומה trumah becomes
טמא... tamei... A בית קברות *Beis Kevaros* a כהן Kohen. *Kohein* is
not allowed to go into altogether and only the question was can
you go in if you take him in this box whereas by
a grave a כהן Kohen. *Kohein* is just prohibited to get within
like to go over it to get within maybe four אמות amos
*Amos* of it but it’s not like he has to completely you
know be completely distant. So it might be somewhat more accessible. So
let’s take a look at what this says. You can make an
עירוב eiruv *Eiruv* for a כהן Kohen *Kohein* who’s טהור *Tahor* because
he’s טהור *Tahor* he’ll be able to eat the תרומה terumah *Terumah*.
If he was טמא tamei, *Tamei* he couldn’t eat the תרומה terumah,
*Terumah* so that would be like a סומכוס Sumchos *Sumchus* problem that
he couldn’t eat his own עירוב eiruv *Eiruv*. So he’s טהור *Tahor*
and the תרומה terumah, *Terumah* is טהור *Tahor* and you can do
it right on top of a grave. And we’re not somehow concerned
that a that’ll make the כהן Kohen, *Kohein* that that and we
somehow assume that the כהן Kohen. *Kohein* will still be able to
get access to the food and that both he and the food
will remain טהור *Tahor*. Okay so how’s this going to happen that
he can get access to this and he and the food will
remain טהור *Tahor*? Let’s take a look. So first the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says היכי אתי *Heichi ati* how does he get to the
food? בשידה תיבה ומגדל *Beshida teiva u’migdal* same story with this box.
Alright so now he’s got to it and he can be even
directly over the grave. But now we’ve got to ask the question:
How does the food remain טהור *Tahor* and how does he get
the food off of the grave? Because as soon as he like
you know whatever reaches out his hand from the box to grab
the food he’s over the grave the food is on the grave.
So how is he going to get to the food? Someone else
gives it to him? Yeah but then you could say that the
whole thing by everything else before. Oh so what’s in a cemetery
someone
else gives it to him. He has to be able to get
to get to it.
Get to it means he has to access it not just he
has to be within a foot of it he has to access
it. So first the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* wants to know how the
food remains טהור *Tahor*. והא כיון דאחתיה איטמיא לה *Veha kivan de’achsa
itamya la* one minute since you put the food down on the
grave it became טמא tamei, *Tamei*. So it says בשלא הוכשרה *Beshelo
huchshara* it’s food that never came in contact with water and therefore
it’s not susceptible for טומאה tumah *Tumah* like it’s an apple after
it’s been picked. An apple an orange or whatever something that never
came in contact with water after it was picked and therefore it
can remain טהור *Tahor*. Does it have to? Because all foodstuffs only
become susceptible to become טמא *Tamei* based on a פסוק pasuk *Pasuk*
in the תורה Torah *Torah* it says כי יותן מים על זרע
על כל kol זרע זרוע אשר יזרע *Ki yutan mayim al zera
al kol zera zeroa asher yizarea*. If water gets put onto a
seed so that only all food is only susceptible to become טמא
*Tamei* if it comes in contact with water after it’s been picked
or let’s say if you שחט *Shacht* a cow the meat comes
in contact after it’s been turned into food you know not while
it’s a cow or while it’s an apple on a tree. So
here the scenario would be it never came in contact with a
liquid and therefore it could be on the grave and be טהור
*Tahor*. One minute או שלא לשה במי פירות *O she’lo lasha be’mei
peiros* or if you’re dealing with bread it was bread that was
made with like you know without any water. It was made with
just apple juice or was made with eggs like they make egg
מצה *Matzah*. So if you use no water then the flour never
came in contact with a liquid so you could even have bread
that is not susceptible becoming טמא *Tamei* if it was not made
with water or it could be our seven liquids but those liquids
are but still there would be things that would be liquids that
are not in those seven eggs apple juice orange juice. And those
types of things you could wind up making bread that would not
be able to become טמא *Tamei*. Charlie wants to say something? Okay
fine. So that’s that’s how the food is טהור *Tahor*. Okay so
wonderful so you’re right over the food the food is טהור *Tahor*
now how do you get to it? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says והא קא מאהיל *Veha ka ma’ahil* and you stick your arm
out of this box to get to the food you’re over the
grave your arm is over the grave and you’re becoming טמא *Tamei*.
So it says דמייתי לה *Demaysei lei* now our version is אחורי
*Achurei* by the back which doesn’t make too much sense. רש"י Rashi
*Rashi* says the version is... I’m sorry I skipped a line. So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says והיכי מייתי לה *Veheichi maysei lah* four
lines from the top how do you get it? How do you
bring it? בפשוטי כלי עץ דלא מקבלי טומאה *Bepashutei k’lei eitz delo
m’kabli tumah* you have a rod like a like you know a
broomstick that doesn’t have any receptacle in it. So wooden vessels that
don’t have any receptacle cannot become טמא *Tamei*. So you stick in
if it were metal it would be. So you stick in not
a metal rod but a wooden rod. No receptacle can’t become טמא
*Tamei*. You stick the wooden rod here you know like over the
grave this is my wooden rod you stick it over the grave
and you push the food towards you. And that’s how you get
it so you so therefore every you know the food is טהור
*Tahor* you’re טהור *Tahor* you you bring it to you and and
therefore you remain טהור *Tahor* and it does and now therefore it’s
a good עירוב eiruv *Eiruv*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says והא
קא מאהיל *Veha ka ma’ahil*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says one
minute but if you’re sticking this rod over then even if the
rod is not does not become טמא *Tamei* because it’s not a
vessel so it’s not טמא *Tamei* going over but it it makes
an אהל ohel *Ohel*. It catches the טומאה *Tumah* right that comes
up from the grave and goes under the rod and brings it
to you. Now it’s assuming that the rod is a טפח tefach,
*Tefach* wide. Actually actually we actually rabbinically say that even if it
is a טפח *Tefach* in circumference even without being a טפח *Tefach*
wide that that אהל ohel, *Ohel* actually is also considered an אהל
ohel *Ohel*. That’s because so you know, just as a rabbinic חומרה.
So if it is that wide anyway, so says even if it's
not טמא, it makes an אהל ohel. and should bring the טומאה
to you. So here the גמרא Gemara says דמייתי
לה אחודיה. d'mayti lei achudei. You bring it. Now again our version
is אחוריה achorei on the back, which doesn't make too much sense.
תוספות Tosafos here says, thank you, is אחודי achudei by the point.
So the basic
idea being that it is not a wide thing, it is a
pole maybe. You could have just said the whole pole is a
טפח, but it's a thin pole, a particularly pole that comes to
a point at the edge. So if it's only the point is
there, obviously there's not enough width at the top that's over the
grave. Basically, the idea is you bring it with a pole that
is not so wide and therefore it doesn't become טמא, it doesn't
serve as an אהל, ohel and you're able to bring it to
you. So we got a perfect solution of how to get it.
So the גמרא Gemara says אי הכי מאי טעמא דרבנן? ei hachi
mai ta'ama d'rabbanan? If that's true, what's the reason of the Rabbis
that would disagree? Meaning this should be a case that they should
agree. So now, so now רש"י Rashi says here, I don't understand.
You know, we had before the Rabbis disagreed by a cemetery. רש"י
Rashi says, yeah, yeah, but by a cemetery we said the issue
was about going in this box and whether a transported אהל counts
as an אהל. But here, we're talking about a single grave, so
you don't need the box. You only need the box if you
want to get over it. But what you could do is even
if you can't be within four אמות amos, of a grave, you
know, here's your grave, you're way over here, you're allowed to be
here, you're outside four אמות, you got a long stick, and you
can bring the stuff to you. So when it's a cemetery, you
can debate whether a transported אהל counts, a transported box.
What's the case if you have a long knife?
Yeah, right. Exactly. So here, what's the debate about? So the גמרא
Gemara says now, you know, you could have said interestingly that the
issue here is, I don't care that you can get the food
to you, you can't get to the food. For the food to
be considered your עירוב eiruv, and the place you began שבת, Shabbos,
maybe you have to be able to get to the food, not
you have to be able to be close to the food and
bring it to you, but the גמרא Gemara doesn't say that. So
let's see what the גמרא Gemara says the issue is about. So
קסברי אסור לקנות בית באיסורי הנאה. kasvari assur liknot bayit b'issurei hana'ah.
You cannot make a, your house in something forbidden in הנאה. hana'ah.
You're not allowed to get benefit from a מת meis and from
anything associated with the corpse, with the grave and anything associated with
the corpse. And therefore,
the problem is that by putting your food on the grave, you're
saying that this is like, this is where I'm starting שבת, Shabbos,
this is my house. So how can you make, you know, the
top of a grave into your house? You're getting benefit from things
that are forbidden in הנאה, hana'ah, things that are associated with the
dead. Well, the גמרא's Gemara gonna get to that. So I should
mention, you know,
apropos
of יום השואה, Yom HaShoah, that there was a lot, you know,
that there were issues around, you know, using some in the Holocaust
museum and in I think יד ושם Yad Vashem about some of
those things that were made out of human skin by the Nazis,
the, you know, I'm sure people have seen those, the lampshades and
those things. You know, so how does that, you know, getting into
issues here, are there halachic problems about איסורי הנאה issurei hana'ah and
so on? Basically, obviously, you know, the answer was not, that it's
not certainly it's not הנאה hana'ah and,
but anyway, but it does touch on these issues. So very appropriate
for today. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. It says
אי הכי מאי טעמא דרבנן דאסור לקנות בית באיסורי הנאה. ei hachi
mai ta'ama d'rabbanan d'assur liknot bayit b'issurei hana'ah. You can't make your
house on top of a grave. That's אסור assur in הנאה. hana'ah.
So וסבר רבי יהודה מותר? v'savar Rabbi Yehuda muttar? So I don't
get it. So what's the other opinion? How can, how can רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda say
you can make your house on top of איסורי הנאה? issurei hana'ah?
So now he says קסבר מצוות לאו ליהנות ניתנו. kasvar mitzvot lav
lehanot nitnu. The מצוות mitzvot
are not considered הנאה. hana'ah. And this assumes that, and we mentioned
this yesterday, that you're only making an עירוב eiruv for the purpose
of a מצוה. mitzvah. So you're making an עירוב eiruv, in order
to get to the other city, I don't know, to attend a
ברית bris or so. And therefore, that's not considered to be a
הנאה. hana'ah. The ability to do a מצוה mitzvah is not a
הנאה. hana'ah. So although the grave enabled you to make this a
place for your עירוב, eiruv ultimately the benefit you accrued was not
considered halachically a הנאה hana'ah because it was only the benefit of
the opportunity to do a מצוה. mitzvah. And mostly הנאה hana'ah is
seen as something that is much more physical, which by the way
connects to the other issue I discussed. You know, there's also questions
about using dead bodies for medical experiments and so on, and is
that איסורי הנאה? issurei hana'ah? And the point that like intellectual types
of benefit, you know, educational, is not considered the הנאה hana'ah that
is forbidden. הנאה hana'ah that's forbidden is much more of the physical
nature. So therefore, the גמרא Gemara says so that's why it's allowed.
קסבר מצוות לאו ליהנות ניתנו. kasvar mitzvot lav lehanot nitnu. You're only
using it to help you do a מצוה. mitzvah. אלא הא דאמר
רבא, ella ha d'amar Rava, so if that's true, how about what
רבא Rava says? מצוות לאו ליהנות ניתנו. mitzvot lav lehanot nitnu. I'm
sorry, that statement that רבא Rava makes, that מצוות mitzvot are not
to derive benefit, are not considered benefit, לימא כתנאי? leima k'tannai? אמר
לשמעתיה, amar l'shmatei, maybe it's his position is really, would he have
to concede that it's a debate... debated by תנאים *Tannaim*? Because the
Rabbis say it's forbidden, so the Rabbis presumably do consider it הנאה
hana'ah. *hana'ah*, right? Again, what's the debate about whether you can put
it on the grave? So it seems like you're saying the debate
is whether that's considered הנאה hana'ah, *hana'ah* or not. So does that
mean that רבא *Rava*'s position that it's not הנאה hana'ah, *hana'ah* is
debated? So אמר לך רבא *amar lecha Rava*, רבא *Rava* would say
to you, אי סבירא להו דאין מערבין אלא לדבר מצוה lidvar mitzvah
*i sevira lehu de'ein me'arvin ella lidvar mitzvah*, had people held, all
the תנאים *Tannaim* held, you can only make an עירוב eiruv *eruv*
for מצוה mitzvah, *mitzvah* purposes, דכולי עלמא מצות matzos לאו להנות ניתנו
*dechulei alma mitzvos lav lehanos nitnu*. Everybody would say that you can
put your עירוב eiruv *eruv* on the grave and it's okay because
מצות *mitzvos*, the benefit of a מצוה mitzvah. *mitzvah* is not considered
a benefit. והכא בהא קמיפלגי *Ve'hacha behacha kamiflegi*. This, what's the debate
of putting it on the grave? This is the debate. מר סבר
אין מערבין אלא לדבר מצוה lidvar mitzvah *Mar savar ein me'arvin ella
lidvar mitzvah*, ומר סבר מערבין אפילו לדבר רשות *umar savar me'arvin afilu
lidvar reshus*. The question is, what are you allowed to make an
עירוב eiruv *eruv* for? One says you can only make it for
a מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah*, so using a grave is not a problem
because it's only giving you מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah* benefit, and the other
says you can make an עירוב eiruv *eruv* even for, you know,
non-obligated
and non-מצוה mitzvah. *mitzvah* purposes, even for, you know, totally your own
discretion. So if that's true, then you cannot use a grave because
then you are getting real benefit; it's allowing you to travel and
it's not just the benefit of a מצוה mitzvah. *mitzvah*. So now
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, אלא *ella*, doesn't that mean that if
it's, let's say, for, I
don't know, you're going
there to get to
a meal? Right, about a ברית bris, *Bris*. Forget about, you know,
הנאה hana'ah *hana'ah*. You're going there to, you know, then everyone would
agree you can't put it on the grave because then it's not
הנאה hana'ah *hana'ah*?
Well, well, forget the grave. If it's not a מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah*,
then according to some you cannot do it because it's not לצורך
מצוה *letzorach mitzvah*. But even though, and even though the actual point
of the עירוב eiruv, *eruv* is to consider that, you know, it's
my food, and the food is הנאה *hana'ah*. In other words, going
to the ברית bris, *Bris*? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* will see,
we'll see that in a minute. Let's see what the גמרא Gemara.
*Gemara* ends. אלא הא דאמר רב יוסף אין מערבין אלא לדבר מצוה
*Ella ha de'amar Rav Yosef ein me'arvin ella lidvar mitzvah*. Okay, but
one minute. That idea that it has to be לצורך מצוה *letzorach
mitzvah*, that actually is not explicitly stated by the תנאים *Tannaim*. That's
a position of רב יוסף *Rav Yosef*. רב יוסף *Rav Yosef* claims
it has to be for the sake of a מצוה *mitzvah*. So
now the way you רבא *Rava* have phrased it, everybody agrees it's
not הנאה *hana'ah*. מצוה הנאה *Mitzvah hana'ah* is not הנאה *hana'ah*. The
question is, are you doing it for a מצוה *mitzvah* for another
purpose? But רב יוסף *Rav Yosef* can't buy into that explanation because
רב יוסף *Rav Yosef*'s position is categorically you cannot do it except
for מצוה *mitzvah* purposes. הא דאמר רב יוסף אין מערבין אלא לדבר
מצוה לימא כתנאי אמרי לשמעתיה *Ha de'amar Rav Yosef ein me'arvin ella
lidvar mitzvah leima ketanaei amre lishmatei*? Is he now going to be
forced to say that his position is debated by תנאים *Tannaim*? Right?
You get it? רבא *Rava* says that everyone agrees מצוה הנאה *mitzvah
hana'ah* is not a benefit, so the debate of using a grave
is whether you can use it for only a מצוה *mitzvah* or
for other purposes. But the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, but one minute,
רב יוסף *Rav Yosef* says you can only use it for a
מצוה *mitzvah*. And the way רבא *Rava* now just set up the
debate, that's exactly what they're debating, whether you can use it for
things other than a מצוה *mitzvah*. Well, רב יוסף *Rav Yosef*, if
he wants to buy into רבא *Rava*, does he have to say
that his position is now debated by תנאים *Tannaim*? So אמר לך
רב יוסף *amar lecha Rav Yosef*, רב יוסף *Rav Yosef* would say
to you, דכולי עלמא אין מערבין אלא לדבר מצוה ודכולי עלמא מצות
לאו להנות ניתנו *dechulei alma ein me'arvin ella lidvar mitzvah u'dechulei alma
mitzvos lav lehanos nitnu*. I don't have to disagree with רבא *Rava*.
I could say, number one, everybody agrees מצות *mitzvos* are not benefit
is not considered benefit, and everybody agrees you can only make
an עירוב eiruv
*eruv* for מצוה *mitzvah* purposes. So if you put those two together,
what should be the problem? Why, what's being debated by putting it
on a grave? So he says, והכא בהא קמיפלגי *vehacha behacha kamiflegi*.
This is the debate. מר סבר כיון דקנה ליה עירוב eiruv לא
ניחא ליה דמינטרא *Mar savar kivan de'kaneh lei eruv lo nicha lei
d'mitnatra*.
One says, look, once this place is קנה kana, *koneh* your עירוב
eiruv *eruv* for you, we're going to see in a minute the
use of the word קנה *koneh*, acquires, but once you establish your
עירוב eiruv *eruv* on this grave, you don't care what happens to
your food afterwards. You only... the whole point of it was to
satisfy the halakhic requirement, and now you're allowed to travel. So the
whole benefit you got out of the grave was it allowed you
to travel and for sake of a מצוה *mitzvah*, which isn't a
benefit. כיון דקנה ליה עירוב eruv? לא ניחא ליה דמינטרא *Kivan de'kaneh
lei eruv lo nicha lei d'mitnatra*. You don't need the food to
be protected. You only did the whole thing just to be satisfied
the rabbinic issue, the halakhic issue. ומר סבר *U'mar savar*, and the
one that says it's a problem holds, ניחא ליה דמינטרא *nicha lei
d'mitnatra*. No, even after the grave allows you to, sort of, make
an עירוב eruv. *eruv*, you want it to be in that region
and you want it to be protected. Why? דאיצטריך לאכילה *De'itzterich l'achila*.
Because if you get hungry on your trip out to the next
city, you can eat your עירוב eruv *eruv*. So therefore you're using
the grave not just to help you do a מצוה *mitzvah*. Even
after it helped you do a מצוה *mitzvah* by making it work
for the halacha of עירוב eruv *eruv*, you're using the grave as
a place to keep your food because you're going to want... might
want that food later. So that's what's debated. But everybody would agree
that if you're just using it for the מצוה *mitzvah*, that A,
that's the only thing you can do an עירוב eruv. *eruv* for
according to רב יוסף *Rav Yosef* with the מצוה *mitzvah*, B, according
to רבא *Rava* that benefit is not considered benefit,
so therefore everybody would agree that in theory it should be okay.
The only question is, are you using it for something else? Now
I should say, and that's why they debate, can you use a
grave? Now if that's true, by the way, I should point out
that has nothing to do with a כהן Kohen, *Cohen*, right? That
then the... those that say no, even not a כהן Kohen *Cohen*
because the problem of using a grave, which, you know, תוספות Tosafot
*Tosafos* points out, yes it's true, but the חידוש chidush *chiddush* was
the one that says it's okay, it's okay not just in terms
of the grave and the איסור הנאה *issur hana'ah*, but even if
it's a כהן kohen, *Cohen*... and even if the food is תרומה,
terumah because of the way we explain that you can get to
the food. Now, I should also point out that, you know, even
if you're going to the other city for the sake of a
מצוה, let's say, I don't know, to attend a ברית, bris, while
you're at the ברית, bris, you're going to have a nice meal,
and you're going to see your friends, and there's going to be
all these other attendant benefits. So that raises an interesting question when
we say מצוות לאו להנות ניתנו mitzvot lav lehenot nitnu about what
happens when you get side benefit while you're doing a מצוה. It
could be that that is not considered, it's a little ironic, but
it could be the מצוה benefit halachically isn't considered a problem as
איסורי הנאה, issurei hana'ah, but it's powerful enough to make the stuff
that's happening with it considered insignificant. So the fact that you happen
to have a nice שמועס shmooze with your friends and you had
a lovely meal at the ברית, bris. that's not considered to be
the primary benefit. The primary benefit because what allowed it anyway was
to allow you to participate in the ברית, bris and that isn't
considered הנאה. So that's an interesting issue is מצוות לאו להנות ניתנו,
mitzvot lav lehenot nitnu, how it sort of, you know, can minimize
the significance of other attendant benefits, and that comes up in a
סוגיא sugya that develops it more. Yes, Charlie.
This is then all about עירוב תחומין. eiruv techumin. You could have
the same argument about עירוב חצרות.
eiruv chatzeirot. No, the issue about whether it's only לדבר מצוה is
only by עירוב תחומין. eiruv techumin. I mean, עירוב חצרות eiruv chatzeirot
was just the general need, you know, to general desire, you know,
need to carry, as we're mentioning before you walked in. I actually
over Sunday had the chance to see the עירוב eruv, exhibit at
the YU Museum. And as I was watching seeing it, I was
going through it and it was very, you know, interesting all the
history and at one point him saying like, yeah, what do they
talk about the whole problem that was without an עירוב, eruv, you
know, the impact that that had on wives and children or whatever.
And then I noticed actually that they had a whole art exhibit
and installation of somebody did exactly around that point, and you know,
they had some videos that discussed that. So the reality is is
that there's a certain amount in which a general עירוב eruv? is
מצוה anyway, to give you that freedom, you know, and that communal
experience on שבת. Shabbos. But that concept of needing it לדבר מצוה
is only discussed by עירוב תחומין. eiruv techumin. Yes, Michael.
Are you going to the people that say, so everyone would agree
the fact that I can eat my עירוב eruv is not considered
הנאה, right?
Well,
the eating of the עירוב eruv. is הנאה, but are you getting
הנאה from the grave? So according to one, you don't care whether
it protects your עירוב eruv, or not, so that's not—the fact that
you happen to get הנאה was not something you were interested in,
you know, that was not how you were using the grave, so
it wasn't forbidden to put it there because that wasn't your intent.
Okay, let's look now to the next משנה. mishnah. So that was
a quite interesting discussion of מצוות לאו להנות ניתנו mitzvot lav lehenot
nitnu and עירוב eruv for sake of a מצוה. We will be
revisiting this issue about whether you can only do עירוב תחומין eiruv
techumin for the sake of a מצוה. And again the point that
I made, which is that even if according to as תוספות Tosafot
says, even if you don't have to be able to eat your
עירוב, eruv, somebody else can eat it, it could be that everybody
agrees you have to be able to have access to it and
to get to it. Yes.
I don't mean to be irreverent or heretical, but couldn't you just
like not put the עירוב on the grave and put it somewhere
else?
I know, but the גמרא Gemara likes talking about these cases because
they're, you know, they're fun to play, you know, to play with
in terms of the
halachic implications. Not every case that the גמרא Gemara deals with is
because it was being somehow, you know, pressured by the practical relevance
of the case. Okay.
And in this debate, because a נזיר nazir and the—and the thing
was in a בית הקברות, beit hakevarot, right?
No, because there's no problem of access. Okay.
משנה. Mishnah. מערבין בדמאי ובמעשר ראשון שניטלה תרומתו. Me'arvin bidmai u'vema'aser rishon
shenitlah trumato. So now we go on to things—we said things that,
you know, all foods you can use, and we discussed potentially problematic
foods, תרומה terumah for a non-כהן. Now we talk about things that
are maybe problematic foods for anybody, but that they're still allowed to
be used. You can make an עירוב with דמאי. demai. דמאי Demai
is grain bought bought from an עם הארץ, am ha'aretz, which means
somebody who's not from the חבורה, chabura, this small group of people
that you know were scrupulous about תרומות ומעשרות. trumot u'ma'asrot. So those
were people that they assume they took תרומה, terumah because even a
tiny bit counts as תרומה, terumah. but it—you had to be concerned
they didn't take מעשר. ma'aser. So you'd have to take your own
מעשר. ma'aser. But you can use that for דמאי, demai, even though
rabbinically you have to take מעשר ma'aser off. You can use that
דמאי demai for an עירוב even though rabbinically you have to take
your own
מעשר. ma'aser. ובמעשר ראשון שניטלה תרומתו, U'vema'aser rishon shenitlah trumato, you can
use מעשר ראשון, ma'aser rishon, which is not holy. It's given to
the לוי, Levi, but it's not holy. So you, I mean, presumably
the לוי, Levi, or if the לוי Levi gave it to somebody
else, can use the מעשר ma'aser but the תרומה terumah was taken
off of, right? The תרומה terumah is the holy part and that's
given to the כהן. But once תרומה terumah was taken off, you
can use מעשר. ma'aser. Now that should seem relatively obvious, which the
גמרא Gemara will ask. ובמעשר שני והקדש שנפדו, U'vema'aser sheni vehekdesh shenifdu,
or מעשר שני ma'aser sheni or something that has been sanctified that
has been redeemed, because then it is what? I know, all this
is פשיטא, pshita, which the גמרא Gemara will ask, but then it
becomes completely,
you know, desacralized—is that a word?—desacralized. והכהנים בחלה, Ve'hakohanim bechalla, and כהנים
Kohanim can
make—can make an עירוב with חלה, challa, they can also make it
with תרומה. terumah Okay, so fine. That idea that it says only
כהנים בחלה Kohanim bechalla suggests like סומכוס Sumchus that not a ישראל,
Yisrael, you have to be able to be the one to eat
it. אבל, Aval, but what— You can't use is לא בטבל, lo
betebel, not grain that is real טבל tebel biblically that you know
תרומות ומעשרות terumot umaasrot hasn't been taken from it, ולא במעשר ראשון
שלא ניטלה תרומתו velo bemaaser rishon shelo nitlah terumato or the first
מעשר maaser without the תרומה terumah. being removed. By the way, I
should say תרומתו, terumato, I think I misstated it before, doesn't just
mean the תרומה terumah was taken from the original grain, it's specifically
תרומתו, terumato, the תרומה terumah of the מעשר. maaser. The לויים Leviyim
have to take a second מעשר, maaser, מעשר מן המעשר, maaser min
hamaaser, and they give a tenth of their tenth to the כהנים.
Kohanim. So that's called תרומת מעשר. terumat maaser. So if the לוי
Levi got his מעשר maaser and has taken the תרומת מעשר, terumat
maaser, then it becomes completely חולין. chullin. But if he has his
מעשר maaser and has not yet taken the תרומת מעשר, terumat maaser,
obviously it's still טבל. tebel. ולא במעשר שני והקדש שלא נפדו, velo
bemaaser sheni vehekdesh shelo nifdu, and not מעשר שני maaser sheni or
הקדש hekdesh that's not been redeemed. Now a lot of this should
seem already relatively obvious. Perhaps the only חידוש chiddush in this is
the דמאי demai case, why you're allowed to use דמאי. demai. I
should say that the next גמרא Gemara we're going to see, pretty
much the entire גמרא Gemara all the way till the next משנה,
Mishnah, is almost like a סוגיא דש"ס sugya deshas that's repeated a
dozen times.
It's almost formulaic. This idea that the משנה Mishnah sometimes says you
can use דמאי demai and מעשר ראשון שנטלה תרומתו maaser rishon she
nitlah terumato and הקדש שנפדו, hekdesh shenifdu, and you can't use טבל
tevel and you can't use it שלא נפדו, shelo nifdu, that is
a type of a phrase that occurs in many משניות Mishnayot that
discusses, you know, that discusses like what types of food you can
use, what type of foods do you make ברכת המזון birchas hamazon
over, any very often it's this list. Here's a list yes and
here's a list no. It's exactly this list in our משנה, Mishnah,
and the גמרא Gemara on it is exactly identical in all places
and discusses why you had to say these things, aren't they all
obvious. So the גמרא Gemara we're going to read is like repeated
almost word for word in multiple places. Okay, so let's take a
look at the גמרא. Gemara דמאי הא לא חזי ליה, demai ha
lo chazi lei, דמאי, demai, how can you use דמאי? demai? You're
not able to eat the דמאי. demai. So the גמרא Gemara says
מיגו דאי בעי מפקיר ליה לנכסיה והוי עני וחזי ליה, migo dei
baee mapkeir lei lenichsei vahavei ani vachazi lei, since if he wanted
to he could renounce ownership over his property and he would become
a pauper and then he'd be able to eat דמאי, demai, because
the rabbis allowed עניים aniyim to eat דמאי, demai, they weren't strict
on the עניים. aniyim. So השתא נמי חזי ליה, hashta nami chazi
lei, now also it's fit for you because in theory you could.
Like the גמרא Gemara before said, in theory you could undo your
נזירות, nezirus, right, remember the גמרא Gemara before said? So in theory
you could be an עני. ani. דתנן, detenan, we taught in the
משנה, Mishnah, מאכילין את העניים דמאי, machilin es haaniyim demai, you can
feed the poor people דמאי, demai, ואכסניא דמאי. veachsanaya demai. ואכסניא, veachsanaya,
you might want to say אכסניא achsanaya means a guest, but actually
רש"י Rashi, says it means like troops that are being quartered, even
if they're Jewish troops. Now the phrase is interesting, it's מאכילין, machilin,
which refers to you are able to give it to them, which
suggests that the primary היתר heter we're focusing on is you're not
transgressing getting benefit from giving it to the poor people. But the
flip side of that is not who's giving but who's receiving. The
poor people therefore are able to eat it, and therefore we infer
from this that the rabbis when they made this requirement to separate
from דמאי, demai, did not make it for poor people, they went
easy on them and therefore in theory it is fit for you.
אמר רב הונא, amar Rav Huna, said רב הונא, Rav Huna, תנא,
tana, we taught in a ברייתא, Beraita, בית שמאי אומרים אין מאכילין
את העניים דמאי ובית הלל אומרים מאכילין את העניים דמאי. Beis Shammai
omrim ein machilin es haaniyim demai uVeis Hillel omrim machilin es haaniyim
demai. That בית שמאי Beis Shammai disagree, you cannot give it to
the poor people and בית הלל Beis Hillel say you can. Now
תוספות Tosafot asks, I don't understand, why do you have to say
you could become poor? Why don't we just say since a poor
person can eat it, it's a good עירוב? Okay, so one answer
might be that our משנה Mishnah sounds like it's סומכוס Sumchus because
our משנה Mishnah says כהנים Kohanim can use חלה, challah, but sounds
like somebody else can't, sounds like you personally have to be able
to eat it. It's not enough that somebody else can eat it.
But the other answer could just be like I said, the גמרא
Gemara, we're reading now is pretty formulaic, this is the same גמרא
Gemara, appears in multiple places in ש"ס. shas. So might here have
had another answer, but this is the answer it gives. Why is
דמאי demai okay? Because in theory you could become an
עני. ani.
You could take תרומה terumah. from the... I'm sorry? You could take
תרומה. terumah
Not,
oh, you mean you take תרומה terumah even on בין השמשות. bein
hashmashos. No, but he's right because even on בין השמשות bein hashmashos
you could take תרומה terumah from דמאי demai and not from... even
on שבת. Shabbos. What? You could be מפריש הספק mafrish hasafek on
שבת? Shabbos? Oh,
that's true.
That's an interesting point. Yes, תוספות Tosafot asks that question too, that
meaning besides that you know that you could in theory you could
have he says right there too exactly that point. תוספות Tosafot at
the bottom דמאי הא חזי ליה. demai ha chazi lei. So תוספות
Tosafot says why don't you just say you could be מפריש mafrish
by you know דמאי demai because you're allowed to be מפריש דמאי
mafrish demai בין השמשות. bein hashmashos. So the answers I think you
can see there for תוספות Tosafot answer but what I think the
answer is is what I said which is this גמרא Gemara. is
word for word in multiple places in ש"ס. shas. So we're not
even though here there's like a more local explanation. The משנה Mishnah
says you're allowed to use דמאי, demai why is that a problem?
But you said you're not allowed to use תרומה.
terumah No, because that you're not allowed to be מפריש mafrish תרומה
terumah בין השמשות. bein hashmashos. So you can't say in theory you
I mean you mean it says you can't use טבל. tevel.
That's your question. Why it say you can't use טבל, tevel, why
don't you say in theory you could be מפריש? mafrish Right, so
that's based on the גמרא Gemara we did yesterday that you're not
allowed to be מפריש mafrish? I mean the גמרא Gemara I mean
asks that but the basic answer is it's a good question but
the basic answer I mean תוספות Tosafot... asks that as word for...
Okay.
It's more complicated. תוספות... Tosafos No. Right, right, תוספות Tosafos asked that.
One of תוספות's Tosafos answers I should say, all right, I'll have
to give, one of תוספות's Tosafos, answers is that which we say
in theory you could eat it, in theory you could be מפריש
mafrish and you could eat it is only if right now in
reality somebody else could eat
it. But טבל tevel which nobody can eat, we don't say in
theory the fact that you could be מפריש mafrish is good enough
to turn it into food. A
כהן cannot eat טבל. tevel. Yes. Right, a כהן, even though it
has the תרומה terumah. in it, חייב מיתה chiyav misa for טבל
tevel even for a כהן. Yes. So okay, bizarre, but yeah.
Okay,
anyway, so the point is is that there are other answers here.
First of all, it could work not like סומכוס Sumchus. although the
משנה Mishnah sounds like סומכוס. Number two, in theory you could be
מפריש mafrish דמאי demai, like the גמרא Gemara said before. You could
do that even בין השמשות. bein hashmashos. But as I'm telling you
תוספות, Tosafos you know, some of the answers to this, the fact
that this גמרא Gemara, is the same גמרא Gemara in multiple places.
So there might be other answers here, but these answers work. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara, says like this: ובמעשר ראשון שנטלה תרומתו.
u've'maaser rishon shenitla terumato.
So how about מעשר ראשון maaser rishon that the תרומה terumah. was
taken from it? So the גמרא Gemara says: לא צריכא. lo tzricha.
No, you need it for the following case. פשיטא peshita says מאי
למימרא, mai l'memra, it's obvious? No, צריכא, tzricha, you need it דהקדימו
בשבולים dehakedimo b'shibolim that the לוי Levi came to the farmer while
the stuff was still in the stalks ונטל ממנו תרומת מעשר ולא
נטל ממנו תרומה גדולה venatal mimeno terumas maaser v'lo natal mimeno terumah
gedolah
and he did take תרומת מעשר terumas maaser from it, that's נטלה
תרומתו, nitla terumato, the תרומת מעשר terumas maaser was taken, but the
תרומה גדולה terumah gedolah was not taken. So basically the לוי Levi
came to the, what normally happens is you cut your wheat, you
thresh it whatever, you make it into a bundle, you bring it
into the house and after you bring it into the barn or
granary or whatever it is and after you bring it inside, that's
when it's obligated and that's when you start distributing the תרומה terumah.
and the מעשר maaser and so on and you take it off.
What happens is this לוי Levi wanted to beat the crowds, so
he came to you while you were still out there in the
fields and chopping and carting it down and he said give me
my מעשר maaser now and you gave it to him. And the
interesting thing is that although it's not obligated yet in תרומות ומעשרות
terumos u'maasros when you give it at that stage, it still works
and it's a legitimate מעשר maaser and you've given your מעשר maaser
now. Now because he came to you at that stage you don't
have to take תרומה terumah first, you can give him straight מעשר
maaser without taking תרומה. terumah He has to take his tenth of
a tenth, he has to take his תרומת מעשר terumas maaser from
it but you did not have to take תרומה. terumah? And that's
the חידוש chidush. that even though the תרומה גדולה terumah gedolah was
not taken, in this scenario it's okay, even though normally without תרומה
גדולה terumah gedolah having been taken it would still be טבל. tevel.
Okay so how do we know this works? וכדרבי אבהו, u'kh'rabbi Abbahu,
like רבי אבהו Rabbi Abbahu says דאמר ריש לקיש, de'amar Reish Lakish,
דאמר רבי אבהו אמר ריש לקיש: de'amar Rabbi Abbahu amar Reish Lakish:
מעשר ראשון שהקדימו בשבולים פטור מתרומה גדולה. maaser rishon shehikdimo b'shibolim patur
mitterumah gedolah. If the לוי, Levi, you know, jumps ahead, jumps the
line and gets his מעשר ראשון maaser rishon while it's still in
the stalks, then you are exempt from תרומה גדולה, terumah gedolah, the
owner can give him the מעשר maaser without taking תרומה גדולה, terumah
gedolah, the main תרומה. terumah? שנאמר: shene'emar: והרמותם ממנו תרומת השם, vaharimosem
mimeno terumas Hashem, this is what it says by the תרומת מעשר,
terumas maaser, the tenth of the tenth
to the
לויים, Leviim, מעשר מן המעשר. maaser min hamaaser. מעשר מן המעשר אמרתי
לך, maaser min hamaaser amarti lecha, a tenth of a tenth I
told you, ולא תרומה גדולה ותרומת מעשר מן המעשר. v'lo terumah gedolah
v'terumas maaser min hamaaser. But you don't have to take תרומה terumah
from your מעשר. maaser. So if you got your מעשר maaser early
you don't have to take תרומה terumah from it. אמר ליה רב
פפא לאביי, amar lei Rav Pappa l'Abaye, רב פפא Rav Pappa said
to אביי: Abaye: What? You mean that a לוי Levi will never
be obligated to take תרומה? terumah. If that's true אי הכי אפילו
הקדימו בכרי נמי. ei hachi afilu hikdimo b'kari nami. Let's say he
beat the כהן, he jumped the line and he got it after
it had been threshed and now that it was in a big
pile of wheat, okay? So would we say also there? I mean
why don't we say anytime if you give the לוי Levi ahead
of the כהן he doesn't have to take תרומה? terumah. אמר ליה,
amar lei, so אמר ליה: amar lei: עליך אמר קרא. alecha amar
kra. No, in response to you the פסוק pasuk says: מכל מעשרותיכם
תרימו את כל תרומת השם. mikol maasroseichem tarimu es kol terumas Hashem.
From all of your מעשרות maasros you should take all of the
תרומות. terumos. So yes from your מעשר maaser you have to take
all of the תרומות, terumos, even the תרומה גדולה. terumah gedolah. I
emphasized the first מכל mikol incorrectly, it's the second כל that has
to be emphasized. From your מעשר maaser you have to take all
of the תרומות, terumos, even the תרומה גדולה. terumah gedolah. So now
we have one פסוק pasuk that says that the לוי Levi has
to take תרומה terumah. if it hasn't been taken and another פסוק
pasuk that we learned that says he doesn't have to take it.
ומה ראית? u'mah ra'isa? What makes you distinguish between one and the
other? Why in one case is he exempt from taking and the
other no? האי אדגן והאי לא אדגן. hai idgan v'hai lo idgan.
One has been already considered grain and the other is not yet
grain. Once it's been transformed into grain, it's been threshed and it's
been made into a pile and it's been smoothed over, then it
becomes, then the obligations of מעשר maaser kick in, of תרומה terumah.
kick in. You're still allowed to eat from it עראי arai temporarily
until you bring it into the house, but the sense is that
now is when there's a חיוב chiyuv of תרומה. terumah. So once
it's been turned into grain, then if you give it to the
לוי Levi the מעשר maaser first he still has to take the
תרומה. terumah It already became obligated in תרומה. terumah But if the
לוי Levi got his מעשר maaser while it was still in the
stalks before it was the grain, then it never yet got into
the obligation of תרומה. terumah terumah and you can finesse that and
bypass the obligation of תרומה. terumah. And he doesn't have to do
it, and he doesn't have to do it, nobody has to do
it. So that when it says that you can do it for
מעשר, maaser, it means even מעשר maaser that was this special case
that got around taking תרומה terumah, from it. Okay. So that's what
the משנה's mishna telling you. מעשר שני והקדש שנפדו, Maaser Sheni ve-Hekdesh
she-nifdu, מעשר שני Maaser Sheni and הקדש Hekdesh that were redeemed. So
again, this is פשיטא, pshita, of course, that they're totally חולין. chulin.
No. צריכא, sricha, you need it, שנתן את הקרן ולא נתן את
החומש, she-natan et hakeren velo natan et hachomesh, that you redeemed it
with the main, with the principal cost, but when you redeem מעשר
שני Maaser Sheni and הקדש, Hekdesh, you're supposed to add a חומש,
chomesh, it's really a quarter, because after you add it, it's a
fifth of the total. Anyway, you're so you're supposed to add an
additional, so you didn't, you just redeemed it with the principal cost.
קמשמע לן דאין החומש מעכב, kamasman de-ein hachomesh meakev, and it teaches
you that not adding that fifth does not prevent the redeeming from
happening. So it still became redeemed and therefore it was now it's
now חולין. chulin. So that's the חידוש. chiddush, אבל לא בטבל, aval
lo be-tevel, you can't use טבל. tevel. פשיטא, pshita, obvious. לא צריכא
בטבל טבול מדרבנן, lo sricha be-tevel tavul mi-Derabbanan, it's only rabbinic טבל.
tevel. Rabbinic טבל tevel is worse than דמאי. dmai. דמאי dmai has
the leniencies of being מפריש בין השמשות, mafreish bein hashmashos, having עניים
aniyim eat it. Rabbinic טבל tevel is considered as טבל tevel itself.
And what would be an example of rabbinic טבל? tevel? וכגון שזרע
בעציץ שאינו נקוב, u-kegon she-zara be-atzitz she-eino nakuv, let's say you grew
it hydroponically, not hydroponically, you grew it in a pot that did
not have a hole in the bottom. So it was in dirt,
but dirt not connected to the ground. Okay, in pots without holes
on the bottom, that is rabbinically obligated. You might also want to
say you grew it like, you know, in ארץ ישראל בזמן הזה,
Eretz Yisrael bizman hazeh, depending on how you feel about whether the
grain right now has
קדושה, kedusha, biblical obligated in תרומות ומעשרות terumot u-maasrot or not. Anyway,
so when it says you can't use טבל, tevel, it means even
rabbinic טבל, tevel, which is worse than דמאי. dmai. Okay. ולא במעשר
שני והקדש שלא נפדו, velo be-Maaser Sheni ve-Hekdesh she-lo nifdu, you can't
use מעשר שני Maaser Sheni and הקדש Hekdesh that have not been
redeemed. I'm sorry, I skipped a line. ולא במעשר ראשון שלא ניטלה
תרומתו, u-velo be-Maaser Rishon she-lo nitla terumato, you can't use מעשר ראשון
Maaser Rishon that does not have the תרומה terumah. taken. פשיטא, pshita,
of course, that's real טבל tevel if it doesn't have the תרומה
taken, presumably meaning תרומת מעשר, terumat maaser, the tenth of the tenth.
לא צריכא שהקדימו בכרי ונטל ממנו תרומת מעשר ולא נטל ממנו תרומה
גדולה. lo sricha she-hikdimo be-kri ve-natal mimenu terumat maaser velo natal mimenu
terumah gedolah. No. Here what it means is was a case where
the לוי Levi jumped ahead of the line, got his מעשר maaser
before the כהן, but got it and he took תרומת מעשר terumat
maaser but he didn't take תרומה. Okay. And he got it though,
not like the earlier case when it was in the stalks, he
got it here when it was already winnowed and grain and in
the pile. Okay. מהו דתימא, mah u detaima, I might think, אימא,
aima, I might think that כדאמר ליה רב פפא לאביי, ked'amar lei
Rav Pappa le-Abaye, maybe that would be good, like רב פפא Rav
Pappa says to אביי, Abaye, maybe if the לוי Levi jumped the
line he never has to take תרומה, you know, תרומת מעשר terumat
maaser he takes but not תרומה. קמשמע לן כדישני ליה. kamasman kedishani
lei. So it's telling you like he answered him, no, that that
special exception is only when he jumped the line and it was
still in the stalks. Once the stuff turns into grain, even if
the לוי Levi jumps the line, he still has to take all
the תרומות, terumot, not just תרומת מעשר, terumat maaser, even תרומה גדולה.
terumah gedolah. ולא במעשר שני והקדש שלא נפדו, velo be-Maaser Sheni ve-Hekdesh
she-lo nifdu, and not if you haven't redeemed מעשר שני Maaser Sheni
and הקדש. Hekdesh. Again it says פשיטא, pshita, obvious. לא צריכא שפדאן
בלא פדאן כהלכתן, lo sricha she-padaan belo padaan ke-hilchatan, you did redeem
them but not correctly. מעשר שפדאן אגב אסימון, Maaser she-padaan agab asimon,
מעשר maaser you redeemed it on a coin that did not have
an image, that was not a minted coin. ורחמנא אמר, ve-Rachmana amar,
and the verse says, וצרת הכסף, vetzarta hakesef, you should bind the
money, כסף שיש לו צורה, kesef she-yesh lo tzurah, only money that
actually has an image on it, that is a minted coin. So
therefore you redeemed it but you didn't redeem it correctly. הקדש שחיללו
אגב קרקע, Hekdesh she-chilalo agab karka, הקדש Hekdesh you redeemed on land.
And land, you cannot use land to redeem הקדש. Hekdesh. דרחמנא אמר,
de-Rachmana amar, because the פסוק pasuk, says, ונתן הכסף וקם לו, venatan
hakesef vekam lo, you should give the money and it should stand
for him. Actually, it's not exactly a פסוק, pasuk. but okay. It's
a sort of like a mashup of two פסוקים. pesukim. Anyway,
here the side here has the פסוק. pasuk. ואם גאל יגאל איש
את שדה הקדישו אותו. ve-im gaol yigal ish et sadeh haktisho oto.
Yeah, it's not a פסוק. Anyway, but nevertheless, we learn that you
cannot redeem it, it has to be on something like כסף kesef
and you cannot redeem הקדש Hekdesh on קרקע. karka. So it's telling
you if you redeemed them but you didn't redeem them correctly, then
it's like they're not redeemed. Okay. רש"י, Rashi Charlie always likes to
point out that the problem of the דרשא drasha of מעשר שני
Maaser Sheni that you need to do it on minted coins is
that there were no minted coins in the world at the time
the תורה was given. Until how many years later? A thousand years
later? Five hundred years
later?
About five hundred years.
Five hundred years
later. Okay. But
that's the power of תורה שבעל פה. Torah She-be'al Peh. Alright. So
now, exactly what I said. I know. Okay.
Anyway, moving on. So as I said, this is a very, this
גמרא, Gemara now that you've learned this גמרא, you can commit it
to memory because you'll see it, you can say it a few
times over בעל פה ba'al peh next time you see this, anytime,
anytime the משנה mishna says... Should have known already. What? I know.
Okay. So anyway, so that's the story. But anyway, these are the
ideas that the food has to be able to be eaten. Next
משנה. mishna. Now we move on from the types of foods, both
in terms of like bread, vegetables, other things, and then the halachic
status of the food to the question of actually placing the עירוב.
And this משנה mishna starts not with a simple case, but with
a more sort of a more interesting case of sending somebody to
place your עירוב and raises and gets us into very interesting discussions
about שליחות, shlichus, about agency. So let's take a look. השולח עירובו
ביד חרש שוטה וקטן. Hasholeach eruvo biyod cheresh shoteh vekatan. Somebody sends
his עירוב to be placed, and he gives it to a חרש,
cheresh, a deaf mute, a שוטה, shoteh, somebody who is considered not
of bright mind, or a קטן, katan, a minor, the people that
halachically are not considered to be בר דעת, bar da'at, considered to
be, you know, people of what's
the, I'm trying to think of a good, sound mind, yeah, but
there's got to be a,
what's the legal sort of secular equivalent? Somebody competent, I guess, is
a competent, or yeah, but what's a minor, what's that considered to
be? Just not the age of majority, I guess.
All right, anyway, okay, people
that are considered anyway to halachically be, to be obligated and of
the right mind, the right mind I should say, not בר דעת
bar da'at is because the significant part here is not that we
think that the קטן katan makes some error in judgment. The relevant
part about these three is that they're not obligated in מצוות. mitzvos.
One because he's too young, and the other because of a question
of being of enough intellect or clear, you know, and you know,
of enough, of enough intellectual ability without getting into the problematics of
חרש cheresh right now. But the common denominator is that they are
not considered to be sort of halachic agents. They're not halachically obligated
or in the category of being able to do things yet halachically.
או ביד מי שאינו מודה בעירוב, O biyod mi she'eino modeh ba'eruv,
or through somebody who just disagrees with the ideas of עירוב. Interesting.
אינו עירוב, Eino eruv, it doesn't count. ואם אמר לאחר לקבלו הימנו,
Ve'im amar le'acher lekablo heimenno,
but if they're not the ones that are actually placing the עירוב,
they're just functioning as like the mailman, they're just delivering it to
the other person and the guy at the other end is going
to take it and place the עירוב, then הרי זה עירוב, harei
zeh eruv, then that works, because they're not doing the significant act
of making it, they're just getting it to the other guy. So
let's take a look at the גמרא. הקטן לא? Haktan lo? Can
the קטן katan not do it? והאמר רב הונא קטן גובה את
העירוב? Veha'amar Rav Huna katan goveh es ha'eruv? Rav Huna says the
קטן katan can take, collect the עירוב? לא קשיא, Lo kashya, it's
not difficult. כאן בעירובי תחומין כאן בעירובי חצירות. Kan be'eruvei techumin kan
be'eruvei chatzeiros. Difference is if it's from an עירוב of this. Why
does it make a difference? So because if anything, you or I
might have been inclined to say that עירובי חצירות eruvei chatzeiros is
more something that requires more of a position of responsibility of an
adult to do because you are sort of taking everybody and joining
them all together and making it like the individual domains are now
all one big domain, whereas by an עירוב תחומין, eruv techumin, you're
just putting some food down at a certain place and because my
food is there, that's where it's like I start Shabbos. That's where
I started Shabbos. So רש"י Rashi says no, that's, it's the opposite.
That when I put my food there, we saw the phrase used
earlier in the גמרא by the grave of קנה, by קנה בית.
koneh bayis. It's like I am acquiring that place to be where
I start Shabbos. So the person who puts the food down, either
me or the person who does it for me, has to be
like they can acquire that place for me, make that my house
for
Shabbos. Whereas the idea of עירוב חצירות, eruv chatzeiros, look, we're all
already pretty much, you know, partners here in the, you know, it's
our joint yard anyway, so there it's more of a formality, it's
not really like creating something new and therefore even a minor can
do it.
It has to be more with the giver than the receiver, right?
It's the בעל הבית ba'al habayis who is giving, you know, who
is
by giving it
to the קטן. katan.
Right, you mean so the דעת da'at of the בעל הבית ba'al
habayis to transfer it? That could also be true. That gets to
issues exactly of דעת אחרת מקנה אותו. da'at acheres makneh oso. That
if the בעל הבית, ba'al habayis, if the one who's doing the
עירוב תחומין eruv techumin is עירוב חצירות eruv chatzeiros
is giving the box of מצות to a קטן, katan, then the
person who's giving it is providing a lot of the necessary דעת
da'at to effect the transfer of ownership. Whereas here it's all being
done by the one who places it at the end and therefore
the original, the you know, the adult is not involved, only the
minor's involved. So that is, but so that is true as well,
yes, that in one place you have more דעת אחרת, da'at acheres,
and רש"י Rashi emphasizes you have more the idea of creating something
new. תוספות says it's because עירוב תחומין eruv techumin is more connected
to a biblical idea. Since the idea of, that's what you were
going to say? Excellent. Okay, so it says because it's connected more
to a biblical idea of לא יצא איש ממקומו, lo yetzei ish
mimkomo, whether we rule it's biblical or not, therefore we're more strict
about it. But whatever it is, a minor cannot do it here,
which is not a חידוש, chiddush the חידוש is that he can
do it by
עירוב חצירות eruv chatzeiros and we'll see more about that when we
get to עירובי חצירות. eruvei chatzeiros. Okay. או ביד מי שאינו מודה
בעירוב, O biyod mi she'eino modeh ba'eruv, or through somebody who doesn't
agree with an עירוב. מאן, Man, who is this? אמר רב חסדא
כותי, Amar Rav Chisda: Kusi, like a Samaritan. Halachically he's Jewish, but
he doesn't buy into this whole rabbinic idea of עירוב, and therefore
we do not let. him be considered a participant in this and
an agent in this. This raises interesting halachic questions in general about
how much does somebody have to sort of buy into it or
be part of a category to do something, like is that an
issue of שליחות, shlichus, is it a general issue of מצוות? mitzvos?
For example, there's a discussion whether
a woman can tie ציצית tzitzis because she's not obligated in ציצית,
tzitzis, although she's an adult and she's Jewish and she's obligated in
מצוות. mitzvos. Right, how much does somebody have to be fully in
the category in order to do a significant act for that or
in order to be an agent for that? Okay, and here sometimes
we do talk about somebody that's like a מומר, mumar, like somebody,
you know, it's an interesting question, somebody who is a מומר mumar
for ברית מילה bris milah and doesn't have a ברית. Hey, what
about somebody who just happens not to have a ברית because I
don't know, he's a hemophiliac or something, can he be a מוהל?
mohel? How about somebody who's a מומר mumar for ערלה, orlah, he
in principle doesn't intend to have a ברית מילה bris milah but
can he be a מוהל? mohel? I don't know why he'd want
to, but can he be a מוהל? mohel? So it's an interesting
question about when is somebody can do a מצוה when they are
categorically out of something, principally out of something, or just by chance
happens not to buy into that whole system. So here we're saying
it with כותים Kuthim but it has broader implications, yes Jordan.
An example, a Reform rabbi shows up and he's the tenth guy
in the room, can I count him for the מנין? minyan?
Okay, so that would be a possible example as well. Okay, so
let's take a look now at the, so anyway, so a lot
of fascinating things here which are not being elaborated on, but one
we're going to focus on is the שליחות shlichus aspect. So let's
take of the קטן katan and so on. Let's take a look.
אמר לאחר לקבלו הימנו, Amar leachar lekablo heimenu, but if you're asking
the חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh shoteh vekatan not to place it but
just to transport it and somebody else is receiving it, הרי זה
עירוב, harei zeh eruv, that's okay because that guy then is the
one that places it. So the גמרא says וליחוש דילמא לא ממטי
ליה, Veleichush dilma lo mamti lei, how do you know? Meaning, forget
halachically that they're not doing a significant act, but how do you
know you can even just trust a קטן? katan? How do you
know they brought it to him, you know? So now maybe that's
a particular question because חרש שוטה וקטן, cheresh shoteh vekatan, maybe it
would be a question about anybody. But anyway, but so even if
they're not needed halachically, how do you know they did the job?
So כדאמר רב חסדא בעומד ורואהו, Keamar Rav Chisda be'omed vero'ahu, like
רב חסדא Rav Chisda says in another context, we're saying that you
saw it, you saw it getting delivered. הכא נמי ירצו בו ועומד
ורואהו, Hacha nami yirtzo bo ve'omed vero'ahu, you saw it got delivered.
So there's no question of the קטן, katan, the only question is
whether they did a halachic act and when they're only sort of
mailmen, it's not a problem. So the גמרא says וליחוש דילמא לא
שקיל מיניה. Veleichush dilma lo shakil minei. But okay, maybe you saw
him then giving over, but maybe the guy didn't accept it from
them? Now maybe you saw him accept it from them, but presumably
it means you're not hearing the transaction, so maybe even though they
gave it to the guy at the other end, he didn't agree
to go ahead and now place it as an עירוב for you.
How do you know what the other guy agreed to? So כדאמר
רב יחייא חזקה שליח עושה שליחותו. Keamar Rav Yechieyo chazakah shliach oseh
shlichuso. הכא נמי חזקה עושה שליח עושה שליחותו. Hacha nami chazakah oseh
shliach oseh shlichuso. Okay,
so רש"י Rashi adds because how, because רש"י Rashi says it's a
חזקה chazakah that the שליח shliach will do what he has been,
the agent will do what he's been told. And here so here
too you can apply it. Now which is the שליח shliach referring
to? So רש"י Rashi says it's the guy, the receiving guy, we
can trust that he's going to do his agency in putting it
down. But who ever made him an agent yet? So רש"י introduces,
which isn't in the גמרא, that this guy who's receiving it, you've
already made this arrangement before שבת Shabbos or whatever. You told him
on Thursday, I'm going to send to you this עירוב, you'll put
it down for me and he agreed to it. Okay, so since
he agreed to it, therefore you can be trust that when he
gets it from the חרש שוטה וקטן, cheresh shoteh vekatan, he'll do
what he agreed to. So if that's true, the גמרא's question of
דילמא לא שקיל מיניה dilma lo shakil minei really means it has
to be re-read. Really the question is, maybe even though he's agreed
to it, maybe he won't actually go through with it. Hard to
read that into the words of לא שקיל מיניה. lo shakil minei.
And it doesn't involve the חרש
שוטה וקטן cheresh shoteh vekatan anymore, it involves the guy at the
end. Right. I know. Right. So that's true. Yeah, it's a funny
question. Anyway, והיכא איתמר דרב חסדא דרב יחייא, Veheicha itmar deRav Chisda
deRav Yechieyo, where was it originally said? אהא איתמר, Aha itmar, the
following thing, דתניא, detanya, נתנו לפיל והוליכו, Nesano lepil veholicho, let's say
you put it on an elephant to bring it to the guy
and the guy's going to take it from the elephant and put
it down. לקוף והוליכו, Lekof veholicho, or onto a monkey, okay, you
might remember some statements about monkeys. ואין זה עירוב. Ve'ein zeh eruv.
So the reason I mentioned that is because it's drawn from a
גמרא, the גמרא uses this idea of elephant and monkey to describe
something in which it sort of like it's not a halachic act,
it just requires getting it somewhere. You can make it into a
paper airplane and throw it, it doesn't matter how it gets there.
Okay, so you put it on an elephant, you put it on
a monkey and they brought it, ואין זה עירוב ve'ein zeh eruv
because nobody received it, they just dropped it off. ואם אמר לאחר
לקבלו הימנו, Ve'im amar leachar lekablo heimenu, but if somebody took it
off of the elephant or the monkey, הרי זה עירוב, harei zeh
eruv, it is good. וליחוש דילמא לא ממטי ליה. Veleichush dilma lo
mamti lei. Now as opposed to before it said דילמא לא שקיל
מיניה, dilma lo shakil minei, which was, which didn't make sense, here
the גמרא's framing it in a way that makes more sense. Maybe
even the guy that takes it off of the elephant or off
the monkey won't place it down like he's supposed to. So אמר
רב חסדא בעומד ורואה *amar Rav Chisda b'omed v'roeh*. I'm sorry. No,
I misread that. ודילמא לא ממטי ליה *u'dilma lo mamti lei*. I'm
sorry, where we are back to what we said before. Maybe they
won't bring it to him. Maybe you put it on the elephant
and the monkey and they didn't get it to the guy. אמר
רב חסדא בעומד ורואה *amar Rav Chisda b'omed v'roeh*. You saw that
it got to the guy. ודילמא לא מקבל הימני *u'dilma lo mekabel
heimanei*. Maybe he won't receive it, which again has to be meant
more abstractly. Maybe he won't do what he's agreed to do. Maybe
he won't place it down. אמר רבי יחיאל חזקה שליח עושה שליחותו
*amar Rabbi Yechiel chazakah shaliach oseh shlichuto*. ואיכא חזקה דשליח עושה שליחותו
*v'ika chazakah deshaliach oseh shlichuto*. And we're going to focus on this
tomorrow. This is a very important halachic issue about when can I
assume if I've told somebody to go ahead and do something that
they actually have done it or not. But right now what we're
saying in the משנה *Mishna* is that a חרש שוטה וקטן *cheresh
shoteh v'katan* cannot do the important act of placing the עירוב *eruv*,
but they can transport it, and anybody can transport it. A monkey
or an elephant can transport it, as long as an adult receives
it and the adult places it down. And then the key question
is going to be two. Number one, can you trust the חרש
שוטה וקטן *cheresh shoteh v'katan* to have actually delivered it? And the
גמרא *Gemara*'s answer is no, you have to observe them delivering it,
you have to observe it being received. But how can you trust
the guy at the end, the adult who's agreed to do it?
That you can trust. חזקה שליח עושה שליחותו *chazakah shaliach oseh shlichuto*.
So if somebody said to you they would do something, that you
can trust. The חרש שוטה וקטן *cheresh shoteh v'katan* not, and therefore
that you have to observe, but an adult yes, and we will
pick up tomorrow with the issue of חזקה שליח עושה שליחותו *chazakah
shaliach oseh shlichuto*. Sure. Yeah. What? Are there general?